只有一种生物
Only one creature
在地球上的每一处栖息地
has carved a life for itself
都能繁衍生存
in every habitat on Earth.
这种生物就是我们人类
That creature is us.
纵观世界
All over the world
今天我们仍在发挥聪明才智
we still use our ingenuity
在远离城市的蛮荒之地  顽强求生
to survive in the wild places, far from the city lights,
直面原始的大自然
face to face with raw nature.
丛林是最富生机  最错综复杂
The jungle is nature at its most vigorous, complex
和最富神秘感的存在
and mysterious.
它或许看上去广袤富饶
It may appear bountiful,
但是对人类来说
but for humans,
这里的环境却惊人地恶劣
this is a surprisingly hostile environment.
不过回溯历史
Though, through history,
人类的伟大文明曾发祥于此
great civilisations have arisen here,
却没能经受住时间的考验
none have stood the test of time.
丛林就是这样桀骜不驯
The jungle refuses to be tamed
惩罚着不守自然法则的人们
and it punishes those who don't live by its laws.
然而今时今日
Yet even today,
有些人却掌握了在原始世界生存的秘密
there are some who guard the secrets of surviving in this wild world.
本片将介绍那些以雨林为家的人们
These are the remarkable stories
非同寻常的传奇故事
of the people who call the rainforest home.
丛林
树林生存者
热带雨林仅仅覆盖了地球表面的2%
Tropical rainforests cover just 2% of the planet's surface,
但地球上一半的物种皆栖息于此
but they're home to half of all species on Earth.
可问题是
The problem is,
很多动物生活在树梢之上
much of this life is in the tree-tops,
让我们难以触及
a world way out of our reach.
要想从地面采获树上的丰富资源
Exploiting the canopy's riches
是极富挑战的
from the forest floor is so challenging,
每天要获得充足的食物都来之不易
getting enough protein is a daily struggle.
巴西的马蒂人捕猎本领高超
The Matis of Brazil are highly skilled hunters
但在过去的几周内
but for the past week
他们猎来的食物只是勉强够分
there's been barely enough meat to go round.
本宁饿着肚子  所以他下决心
Benin is hungry and he's determined
今天的狩猎必须收获更多
today's hunt will be more successful.
他把树蛙的毒素
Administering tree-frog toxin
注入血流当中  促使他的身体
into his bloodstream purges his body,
为狩猎做好准备
preparing it for action.
毒素能使我们更加强壮和迅速
...这样我们就能追上逃跑的动物了
马蒂人还在眼睛里滴入一种有毒的树汁
The Matis also drop a noxious plant juice into their eyes
来刺激自己的意识
to sharpen their senses
把注意力集中在狩猎上
and focus their minds on the hunt.
小鸟飞得快...
野鸡跑得快...
野鹿跑得快
本宁和其他人借此召唤动物的精髓附身
Benin and the others summon the power of the animal spirits.
从地面捕捉树上的动物
Hunting canopy animals from the ground
需要借助强大的火力
requires formidable fire power,
一根4米长的吹管
a four-metre long blowpipe,
经过了几千年的精密加工和打磨
precision-made to a design honed over thousands of years.
我们继承了族人的狩猎技术...
这些来自我们的先辈们...
我们花上好些年来掌握
要在茂密的植被中寻找猎物是很艰难的
Spotting animals in the dense vegetation is so hard,
马蒂人只能依靠听觉来确定猎物的位置
the Matis rely on hearing to locate prey
用模仿来引诱它们进入狩猎范围
and use mimicry to lure them into range.
他们能模仿森林里
They can imitate all ten
全部数十种猴子的叫声
species of monkey found in these forests.
一只吼猴在应和
A howler monkey responds.
在30米高的地方
30 metres up,
猴子们在一颗无花果树上进食
monkeys are feeding in a fig tree.
用食人鱼的牙齿打磨飞镖
Scoring the darts with piranha teeth
能确保有毒的箭头刺穿猎物的身体
ensures the poisoned tip breaks off in the victim's body.
与猎枪不同  吹火管几乎无声
Unlike guns, blowpipes are near silent
发射时不会惊动到猴子
and can be fired without spooking the monkeys.
本宁射中第一枪
Benin makes the first hit,
现在猴子们仓皇而逃
and now the monkeys scatter.
一旦射中  箭毒便发挥作用
Once shot, the monkeys must be tracked
猴子就一定能被追踪到
as the curare-vine poison takes effect.
这只猴子已经很虚弱了
This monkey's already weak,
它仍躲藏着  但必然被驱赶出来
but it's hiding, and must be flushed out.
他们又射了一枪
They shoot again.
它被一根树藤缠住了
It's stuck in a vine now,
他们只有爬上去取它下来
and there is no choice but to go and get it.
第一只收入囊中  但这只是开始
One down, but it's just the beginning.
作为最敏捷的猎手之一
As one of the swiftest hunters,
抓获逃脱的猴子是本宁的职责
it's Benin's job to pick off any escaping monkeys.
他射向了另一只  但没射中
He shoots another, but misses.
本宁又发了一枪
Benin fires again,
这一次命中目标
this time on target.
这只猴子终于停了下来
The monkey finally stops
本宁瞄准最后一只
and Benin takes aim one last time.
8只猴子
Eight monkeys.
今天是满载而归的一天
It's been a good day.
但其实他们经常空手而归
But all too often they return empty-handed.
这让我非常高兴...
能把肉食带回去给家人
高空捕猎是非常困难的
Hunting in the canopy is so difficult,
因此大部分的食物  必须在地面寻求
people must find most of their food closer to the ground.
可单单靠地面上的猎物谋生
But scratching a living on the forest floor
也不会容易到哪去
is hardly any easier.
这个神秘的世界  本就错综繁复
The complex nature of this mysterious world
难以驾驭
is so hard to master,
这一点  必须尽早明晰
the lessons have to start early.
奥兰多  来自委内瑞拉皮亚拉奥部落
Orlando's from the Piaroa tribe of Venezuela.
他和其他的孩子一样
He's like any other kid,
在丛林里的朴素生活
only life in the jungle
已经迫使他学会自谋生计
has already forced him to fend for himself.
如果家里没有食物了...
我就得去打猎
但是这样的童年冒险经历
But this childhood adventure
带他们进入到丛林深处
takes them deep into the jungle underworld.
由于只有2%的阳光能够到达地表
As only 2% of sunlight reaches the forest floor,
因此只有极少数的植物生长与此
surprisingly few plants grow
这也意味着  极少的动物在此活动
and this means few animals.
这里的食物甚至比沙漠地区还要少
There's less protein here than in the desert
并且很多还是有毒的
and much that is here is poisonous.
这里什么也没有
区分有毒食物是一项必需的生活技能
Distinguishing dinner from danger is an essential life skill.
这里看起来不错
几乎没有什么生物
Few creatures have a more
比他们寻找的  更令人望而生畏
sinister reputation than the one they seek.
这种巨大的狼蛛
The goliath tarantula,
和餐盘一样大
the size of a dinner plate,
是世界上最大的蜘蛛
the largest spider in the world.
这样的晚餐  简直让人倒胃口
It's hard to imagine a less appetising meal,
但挑食的人  是无法在丛林里存活的
but picky eaters don't last long in the jungle.
把树叶给我
何况  奥兰多说它们很美味
Besides, Orlando says they're delicious,
捕捉这样危险的动物  也是分区域的
and handling dangerous animals comes with the territory.
大概从五岁起
From about five years old,
皮亚拉奥部落的孩子就知道该去哪捉蜘蛛
Piaroa children know exactly where to hunt for spiders
而且几个小时内就能抓到足够一餐的数量
and in a couple of hours can catch enough for a decent meal.
但是他们必须小心蜘蛛巨大的毒牙
But they have to be careful of both the huge fangs
和它们向侵犯者喷发的体毛
and of the hairs they kick towards any attacker.
小心点  不然这些毛会刺到我们
如果这些毛接触到肌肤或者被吸入体内
If they contact the skin or are inhaled,
会令人痛苦难忍
they cause a nasty reaction.
我被刺到了
抓住它
奥兰多不幸被刺
Orlando's come off worst.
我痒极了
但是在这个丛林里长大
But growing up in the jungle,
他早就适应了这种微小的不适
he's used to a little discomfort.
我们把它吃了然后就睡觉去
狼蛛最适合烤着吃  尝起来像棉花糖
Tarantulas are best served toasted, like marshmallows.
棉花糖是一种生长在非洲的植物
所有的毛发必须烤至脱落
All the hairs must be singed off
这样就不会卡在喉咙里
so they don't catch in the throat.
随着关节部位被渐渐烤干
And when they start squeaking,
它们会发出甑南焐
which is just air escaping from the joints,
他们快弄好了
they're almost done.
烤蜘蛛总是发出这样的声音
我的已经好了
狼蛛吃起来有点像螃蟹
Tarantulas taste a bit like crab
而且  加上一点佐料  将会十分美味
and, with a little seasoning, they go down a treat.
罗索娜  把辣酱递给我
奥兰多和他的朋友们能够生存下来
Orlando's and his friends' survival
在于他们能把握住森林中每一次机会
depends upon embracing every opportunity in the forest.
居住在丛林里的人们十分依赖周边的环境
Jungle people rely so heavily on their surroundings,
他们已经融入成为森林的一部分
they become a natural part of the forest
并于大自然建立了非同寻常的联系
and form extraordinary bonds with nature.
很少会有人比亚马逊东部的阿毋瓜嘉人
Very few people live more intimately with animals
与动物更亲密
than the Awa Guaja of the eastern Amazon.
他们饲养了一系列的来自森林的生物
Nurturing a wide range of creatures from the forest,
痴迷地喂养宠物
the Awa are obsessive pet keepers.
有一些动物比另外一些更受珍惜
And there are some animals they cherish above any others.
与马蒂人一样  猎猴对阿毋人的生存极为重要
Like the Matis, hunting monkeys is vital to the Awa's survival,
这为他们提供将近一半的食物
providing nearly half their protein.
但是  这种关系远不止是提供食物
But this relationship provides far more than food.
恩维不仅仅吃猴子
Emwi not only eats monkeys,
她深爱着它们
she loves them.
我喜欢养猴子
如果杀死一只母猴...
我会把它的孩子养作宠物
宠物并不好吃
我们只吃从森林打回来的猴子
几乎所有的阿毋家庭
Almost all Awa families
都会饲养一些猴子作为宠物
keep a number of monkey pets.
在村落里有8个不同的种类
There are eight different species in the village.
阿毋人对猴子表现出特别的温柔
The Awa show extraordinary tenderness for the little monkeys,
他们更相信它们是人类的一员
believing they're more human than animal.
恩维是个尽职的母亲
Emwi is a devoted mother,
不论是对她的孩子还是猴子
both to her children and her monkeys.
这就像用母乳喂养一个小孩
它不会伤害你  因为它已经被驯服了
对恩维和其他的阿毋人来说
For Emwi and the other Awa,
用母乳喂养猴子
breastfeeding monkeys
只是帮助有需要的孤儿的
is simply a natural way
一种天然的方式
to help an orphan in need.
如果我不哺育它...
它就会死的
对一种经常捕杀的动物
Caring so intimately for an animal
给予如此细微的照顾
they regularly kill
可能听起来自相矛盾
may appear contradictory,
但是阿毋人相信  他们从雨林里索取什么
but the Awa believe for everything they take from the forest,
就得归还什么
they have to give back.
当我们的生活与动植物
When our lives are so deeply entwined
如此紧密地纠缠在一起
with animals and plants,
它们就必然成为伟大灵感的来源
they inevitably become a great source of inspiration.
效仿自然最为壮观的文化案例
Perhaps the most spectacular case of culture imitating nature
也许就发生在巴布亚新几内亚
is found amongst the people of Papua New Guinea.
丛林深处
Deep in the forest,
一只极品雄性天堂鸟
a male superb bird of paradise
向一只土土的雌鸟展示自己华丽的羽毛
struts his stuff for a rather drab female
但她却不是唯一的观众
but she isn't the only one watching.
葛林是天堂鸟捕手
Geling is a bird of paradise hunter,
他想要的是价值极高的羽毛
and it's the highly prized feathers he's after.
多美的羽毛啊
真是一只极品鸟
这些令人垂涎的羽毛被一代代传递下去
These coveted plumes are passed down through generations
但是偶尔损坏的需要用新的替代
but occasionally damaged ones need replacing.
然而  天堂鸟极其难捕获
Birds of paradise are so hard to hunt, however,
因此葛林需要援手
that Geling's enlisted help.
佩卡相中的是公主长尾风鸟的长尾羽
Peke is after the long tail feathers of the Princess Astrapia,
他用水果引诱它们现身
and he's using fruit to lure them in.
明天可是葛林的大日子
Tomorrow is a big day for Geling.
他的族人将在晒晒大会上表演
His clan will be performing at a Sing Sing,
他的声望及全村荣誉的评判标准
where his reputation and the honour of his village
都在于他羽毛收藏的优劣
will be judged on the quality of his feather collection.
晒晒大会比的就是
Sing Sing events are all about competing
谁穿着最佳
to see who's the best-dressed,
葛林知道漂亮的羽毛必不可少
and Geling knows not a plume can be out of place.
羽毛让人引人注目...
这次我一定是最夺目的
在鸟类和人类当中
In both birds and humans,
最吸引人眼球的那位  得到最多的关注
it's the most eye-catching who gets the most attention,
尽管葛林可能高估了他的战利品
though Geling might be overstating his conquests.
晒晒大会上会有六七个娘儿们追着我
我都无从选择...
是一次全上...
还是每晚上一个轮一周
海根山区的晒晒大会
The Mount Hagen Sing Sing
是世界上最大的丛林主题的盛装派对
is the world's largest jungle-themed fancy-dress party.
有几百个部落参加
Attended by hundreds of tribes,
是新几内亚全国最大的盛事之一
it's one of New Guinea's biggest national events.
穿梭人流之中
Amidst the mayhem,
葛林给自己的服装添上最后的点睛之笔
Geling's putting the finishing touches to his outfit.
戴着我的头饰...
让我整个人感觉自豪又富有
在新几内亚  男性的虚荣是可炫耀的
In New Guinea, male vanity is something to flaunt.
尽管每个部落都有自身的风格
Though each clan has its own style,
但几乎所有人都加入了
almost all wear bird of
天堂鸟羽毛  为头冠增光添彩
paradise feathers as their crowning glory.
他们的着装  甚至求爱舞蹈
In their looks, and even their courtship dances,
人类和鸟类的一致特征一目了然
the parallels between man and animal are unmistakable.
他们是戴着羽毛的鸟类
They're birds of a feather.
两者都用珍贵的羽翼来展示健康和美丽
Both use these precious plumes to display fitness and beauty.
站上中央舞台  是葛林炫耀的时候了
Taking centre stage, it's Geling's turn to show off.
要花好多年头才能攒下这么多羽毛呢...
会被认为是部落里有身份的人
这种和天堂鸟之间密切的联系
This deep connection with
始于4万年前
birds of paradise began 40,000 years ago
却没有一点式微的迹象
and it shows few signs of fading.
葛林有点兴奋
Geling's getting on a bit,
而他的仰慕者们
and his female admirers
并不像过去的那么多
aren't quite as plentiful as they used to be,
但他还是一心展示他的羽毛
but he's not going to let that ruffle his feathers.
热带雨林的多样性特质
The diverse nature of the rainforest
在方方面面都影响着居住其中的人们
influences the people who live here in endless ways
并且经常带来令人赞叹的结果
and it often leads to breathtaking results.
对于非洲刚果盆地的巴亚卡部落来说
For the Bayaka tribe of Africa's Congo basin,
丛林的声音对他们的启发最大
it's the sounds of the jungle that most inspire them.
要么把河流当成架子鼓
Whether using a river as a drum kit,
要么配合动物的鸣叫合唱工作小曲儿
or incorporating animal calls into their work songs,
巴亚卡人把音乐
the Bayaka consider music
当作雨林最大的赐予
to be their greatest gift from the forest.
但是这里还有一种东西
But there's something else
让巴亚卡人趋之若鹜
found here the Bayaka prize just as highly.
其价值之高以至于他们愿意用生命去交换
So highly they're prepared to risk their lives for it.
特特和蒙公杰去狩猎了
Tete and Mongonje are on the hunt,
但他们并不是奔着肉食去的
but it's not meat they're after.
蒙公杰  看啊  那里有个蜂窝
蜜蜂们都冲这边来了  在那根树枝上
就在那根树枝上
-可是实在太高了
-但我老婆好久没吃过蜂蜜了
她生气了吗
是啊  火大得很
蜂蜜对巴亚卡人来说就是液体黄金
Honey is liquid gold to the Bayaka,
他们不畏高度去采集蜂蜜
and they go to extraordinary lengths to gather it.
凭借一根特制的藤条
Using a special vine,
特特用它作为辅助
Tete makes a harness to help him
爬上这棵高达40米的树
get to grips with this 40-metre tree.
像他这样爬树需要技巧  力量和耐力
Climbing like this requires skill, strength and stamina,
特别是在热带炎热的天气下
especially in the tropical heat.
特特爬树时
While Tete climbs,
蒙公杰燃起了一大堆树叶
Mongonje prepares a bundle of smoking leaves
来安抚蜜蜂们的不安
to help pacify the bees.
一个小时过去了  特特已经爬到很高了
An hour's passed and Tete's making impressive progress.
但是他还有一大段距离
But he's still got a way to go.
发现蜂蜜的消息传得很快
News that honey's been found has spread quickly,
特特的妻儿都前来围观
and Tete's wife and kids come to watch.
爬树的时候...
必须把脑子里的害怕全部清空
特特终于到达了树冠
Tete's finally made it to the crown of the tree
但是为了更前一步
but to go any further
他必须离开藤条的保护
he'll have to leave the security of his vine.
你越害怕  越是容易掉下去
很多朋友们都是这样摔死的
特特清楚地知道采集蜂蜜的危险
Tete's fully aware how dangerous honey gathering is,
但是巴亚卡人认为无勇气  不男人
but the Bayaka believe it's bravery that makes the man,
雨林里能找的甜食如此稀少
and sugar is so scarce in these forests
蜂蜜已是特特能为家里提供的最好的营养品
that honey is the best nutrition Tete can provide for his family.
我家特特最棒了
孩子们一点也不担心他
只有自豪
他们会说  瞧老爸多棒
远在40米的高空  完全没有保护措施
40 metres up, and unattached,
特特每一步都要很谨慎
Tete can't put a foot wrong.
现在蜜蜂们开始袭击他了
And now the bees are beginning to attack.
他已经到达了蜂窝
He's made it to the hive,
但他必须赶在蜜蜂大批袭来之前取到蜂蜜
but he's got to get at the honey before being overcome by bees.
烟雾有点效果  但是特特还是被蛰了
The smoke helps, but Tete's still being stung.
终于  特特采到了珍贵的蜂蜜
Finally, Tete strikes gold.
收获真不错...
好多蜂蜜呢
特特的家人收到了第一篮蜂蜜
The first basket goes down to Tete's family
几千只愤怒的蜜蜂们
and even thousands of angry bees
也影响不了这顿美味
can't stop the feast.
蜂蜜可好吃了
...非常好吃
我老公心肠很好
他经常给我采蜂蜜吃
特特并不着急下树  品尝着自己的胜利果实
Tete takes time to savour his success.
他做的够多了  让老婆孩子甜了嘴
He's done enough to keep his wife sweet, treat his children
并且还赢得了族人的尊敬
and earn respect from his tribe.
对雨林人民来说
For forest people,
简单的东西也有着巨大的价值
simple things can hold extraordinary value,
但是正是这些树木本身
but it's the trees themselves
在世界范围内需求巨大
that are most in demand around the world.
伐木是全世界雨林地区
Logging is one of the greatest threats
面临的最大威胁之一
facing the world's rainforests.
但也有少数地区
Yet there are a few places
伐木带来的破坏力并不那么大
where its effects are far less destructive.
印度和缅甸交界处的雨林木材
The jungles bordering India and Burma are harvested
就是用最环保的方式开采的
using one of the most forest-friendly methods of all.
它借助了雨林中最强大生物的
And it involves harnessing the raw power
原生态力量
of the mightiest creature in the jungle.
这是兰普萨
This is Ramprasad -
一头重达5吨半的雄性亚洲象
five-and-a-half tonnes of bull Asian elephant.
这是苏米尔  他的主人
And this is Sumir, his mahout.
干得不错哟  兰普萨
天黑之前  他们需要将2吨重的原木
Before nightfall, they have to drag a two-tonne log
搬出林子外三公里的地方
three kilometres out of the forest.
兰普萨是队伍里最强大的一头象
Ramprasad is the mightiest elephant in the camp,
但这任务依旧是
but it's still a mammoth test
对蛮力和彼此交流的巨大考验
of brute strength and communication.
苏米尔通过100多种口令指挥兰普萨
Sumir steers Ramprasad with over 100 different commands.
右边点  再右点  行了
他可以听得懂北印度语  阿萨姆语
He can be operated in Hindi, Assamese
甚至还懂一点点英语
and he even understands a little English.
苏米尔也是驾驭大象的老手了
And Sumir's pretty fluent in elephant too.
我能通过他的肢体语言...
了解他的情绪
你这头老象  别跟孩子一样
不可思议的强壮  加上令人吃惊的灵活性
Unbelievably strong and surprisingly nimble,
在这种复杂的地形区
elephants are far superior
大象是搬运木材的最佳选择
to logging machines in this tangled terrain.
更重要的是
Most importantly,
没有必要为了运送几棵选好的木材
the forest doesn't have to be completely cleared
就清出一大片森林开道
just to access a few selected trees.
要是把大机器开进来...
会完全毁了这片林子
直走
完全没有必要更换昂贵的零件
There's no need for expensive spare parts,
大象们百分百低碳环保
and elephants run on 100% green fuel.
但是  和机器不一样的是
But, unlike a machine,
兰普萨有自己的思想
Ramprasad has a mind of his own
他需要受到敬重
and must be treated with respect.
大象们可是强大得很呐
很多人因此丧命...
正是因为不理解他们的象
在让大象工作前  将它们驯化至关重要
It's essential to break elephants in before they're put to work,
但他们内心仍然狂野
but they're still wild at heart,
而掌控好这样的原始动物  讲究的是
and keeping control of such raw might is a fine balancing act
命令它们与怜惜它们的微妙平衡
of command and compassion.
苏米尔和兰菩萨及时到达了采集地
Sumir and Ramprasad make it to the collection site in good time
还帮助卡车装卸木头
and help load the trucks.
将原木运输到锯木厂
Transporting logs to the sawmill
是全过程唯一要用到机械的地方
is the only mechanised part of the entire process.
但他们还没法走出森林
But they're not out of the woods yet.
又一次  在这丛林环境下
Once again, under jungle conditions,
大象的作用超过了机动车
elephants out-perform engines.
工作完成  该好好洗个澡
Job done, time for a well-earned wash.
东印度和缅甸的丛林
The jungles of East India and Burma
形成了亚洲最大的雨林地带
form the largest area of rainforest left in Asia
为最后一小群健康的亚洲象
and provide sanctuary for the last healthy population
提供了庇护所
of Asian elephants.
兰菩萨和其他大象已经失去了自由
Ramprasad and these other elephants have lost their freedom,
但这种伐木方式保全了它们物种的未来
but this way of logging helps secure the future of their species
以及它们的家园
and their home.
正是靠这种与自然合作的关系
It's through partnerships with nature
人们才能在不破坏丛林的前提下
that people manage to live within the jungle
生存下去
without destroying it.
但是在大多数热带雨林区
But in most areas of tropical rainforest,
画面并不这样和谐
the picture is not so harmonious.
在短短50年里
In just 50 years,
地球上一半的热带雨林已被砍伐殆尽
half the planet's tropical forest has been cleared.
每天有多达一百个雨林物种走向灭亡
As many as 100 rainforest species go extinct every day,
许多还未被人类发现
often before they've even been discovered.
我们失去的不只是动植物
And it's not just animals and plants.
那些我们一无所知的人类文明
We're also losing human cultures
也包括在内
that we know almost nothing about.
即便是在21世纪
Even in the 21st century,
仍有一些人
there are still people who
隔绝于其他人类而独立存在着
exist in isolation from the rest of humanity,
并且基本全都住在丛林里
and virtually all live in jungles.
这些广阔的  未经勘探的森林
These vast, unexplored forests
是地球上唯一一个能让整个部族
are the only places left on Earth
安居并不被发现的地方
where entire communities can live undetected.
巴西是70多个原始部落的聚集地
Brazil is thought to be home to around 70 isolated tribes,
占到世界总数的三分之二
around two-thirds of the world total.
琼斯・卡洛斯・梅尔雷斯在FUNAI工作
Jose Carlos Meirelles works for FUNAI,
一所专门保护巴西土著居民的政府机关
a government agency that protects Brazil's indigenous people.
今天  他希望能遇上某个原始部落
Today, he's hoping to encounter one of these uncontacted tribes.
你现在必须转身
快掉头
他要赶在别人之前找到他们
He needs to get to them before others do.
我们的职责是监管好这片区域...
确保没人来打搅他们...
让他们能过着安宁的生活
伐木业和采矿业正蚕食着这些森林
Logging and mining are encroaching on these forests
还有人极力否认
and there are some who want to deny
有原始部落居住在这
that uncontacted tribes live here at all.
这些部落可能会被铲平...
就跟拍死一只蚊子一样轻而易举...
没人会注意到
可以了  差不多到了
梅尔雷斯需要证据
Meirelles needs evidence.
保护这些人民的斗争
The fight to protect these people
需要证明他们的存在  并公之于众
depends upon proving and publicising their existence.
一张他们的照片...
就能胜过千言万语
眼见为实
这绝对是第一个
This is the very first
对原始部落的航拍镜头
aerial footage of an uncontacted community.
这些人生活在21世纪...
简直太不可思议了
他们的生活方式以及
Very little is known about their way of life
他们的语言我们都知之甚少
or even their language,
而梅尔雷斯宁愿他们永远保持原状
and Meirelles would rather it stays that way.
他为保护原始部落不受外界干扰
He's dedicated 40 years to protecting
贡献了自己四十年的光阴
isolated tribes from the outside world,
但这可不像由他们自生自灭那么简单
but this isn't as simple as just leaving them alone.
他们的未来由不得自己
而是取决于我们  我们的企图
如果非法矿工和伐木工遇到了这些人...
他们不会对他们拍照...
而是会扣动扳机
使用稳定的变焦镜头
Using a stabilised zoom lens,
就可以在一公里外进行拍摄
it was possible to film from a kilometre away,
来减小对他们的打扰
minimising disturbance.
梅尔雷斯认为  越多人知道
Meirelles believes the more people are aware
这些部落的存在
these tribes are here,
保护他们生存方式的斗争  就越有效
the more effective the fight to preserve their way of life.
人类中有这群人的存在是很重要的
他们时刻提醒着我们...
人可以有不同的活法
他们是地球上最后一群不受约束的人
这些人靠融入森林的本领得以生存
Humans have survived here by becoming part of the forest,
但正是这种对森林的依赖性
but it's this specialisation
让他们在这变幻莫测的时代显得如此脆弱
that leaves them so vulnerable in these changing times.
这些人掌握着
These people are the guardians
能让人类在大自然中谋得生路的
of a wealth of knowledge and skill
难得的知识和技能
that enable humans to forge a life within the natural world.
像遥远的西巴布亚部落那样
And there are very few whose existence remains
与雨林关系紧密的原始人
as intimately connected with the rainforest
已经寥寥无几了
as the remote tribes of West Papua.
科罗威部落完全适应丛林生活
The Korowai are so adapted to life in the jungle,
他们以树木为生
they've taken to the trees.
这个部落正在建造一座新房子...
This clan is building a new house...
但绝不是一座普通的房子
...but it will be no ordinary one.
所有物料都是就地取材
All materials must be sourced on site,
砍伐中大量使用的仍是石器时代的工具
and much of the cutting is still done using Stone-Age tools.
这是个雄伟的工程
It's an ambitious project.
计划是在一棵35米高的树上
The plan is to build their new home
建造他们的新家
in a tree 35 metres up.
幸好他们选中了一棵铁木
Just as well they've chosen an ironwood,
是森林中最结实的树木
the strongest tree in the forest.
第一步是要建一副直达树冠的梯子
The first step is to build a ladder to its crown.
这是世上唯一几个住在树屋上的部落
These are the only tribes in the world who live in tree houses
他们这么做也是事出有因
and they do so for a number of reasons.
它可以抵御洪水来袭
It's an escape from the floods
和森林地表咬人的昆虫
and the biting insects on the forest floor.
它保护他们不受敌人攻击
It offers protection from enemy attack,
但最重要的是
but most of all,
这是他们超凡的丛林技艺的体现
it's a display of their jungle prowess.
对科罗威人来说  房子越高
For the Korowai, the higher the house,
威望就越高
the greater the prestige.
科罗威人的技艺也许是独一无二的
The Korowai's skills may be exceptional,
但世界上的建筑工人都大致相同
but builders are the same the world over.
能休息一下感觉真好
让我们抽根烟吧  谁有火
别闹了
万一我们掉下去  那必死无疑啊
作为部落中最强壮的攀登者
As one of the clan's strongest climbers,
卫欧作为监工  监督着最危险的工作
Wayo is the foreman overseeing the most dangerous jobs.
我们把这绑起来
把这枝和那枝砍掉
小心点
这树太高了  我们最好当心点
削掉树枝能让
Thinning the branches keeps
房子在刮风时不被吹散
the house from shaking apart in the wind.
掉下去就意味着必死无疑
A fall would mean certain death,
但在树顶站稳是科罗威人的第二天性
but teetering in tree-tops is second nature to the Korowai.
我就知道一个人...
从树屋上掉下来摔死了
在搭建房屋的进程中
As the house goes up,
更多树倒了下来
more trees come down.
但它们必须从正确的方向倒下去
But they have to fall in the right direction.
施工活动紧锣密鼓地进行
Activity on the building site is intense.
雨季很快就要来了
The rainy season is fast approaching
还需要加盖屋顶
and the roof still needs to go on.
每个人都在为完成进度竭尽全力
Everyone's pulling their weight to complete on schedule.
当我们建造树屋时...
我们的邻居都会来帮忙
当然...
我们会给与回报
房顶是用西谷椰子的树叶平铺加盖的
The roof is tiled with sago-palm leaves
地面和墙面用树皮绉做成
and rolls of tree bark make the floor and walls.
就算很重也没问题  我壮着呢
我不会掉下去的
两周的时间  42个人
In two weeks, with 42 workers,
砍倒了数不清的树
countless felled trees,
用了30捆棕榈叶
30 bundles of palm leaves,
16捆树皮和5千米长的麻绳
16 rolls of bark and 5 kilometres of twine,
新家完工了
the new home is complete.
是时候搬进去了
It's time to move in.
和往常一样  严格的准入政策
As always, modesty dictates
反映了原始人的朴质
a strict entrance policy.
女人总是第二个进去...
这样男人就不能看到她们的裙底
每样东西都要搬进去  包括宠物
Everything must be carried up, even family pets
要是忘带了什么  下去一趟可够你受的
and it's a long way back down if you forget something.
乔迁仪式是点起第一把火
The first fire is ceremonially lit,
对于木质树屋来说
an interesting way
真是个有趣的祈福方式
to bless a wooden tree house,
但健康和安全常识
but health and safety regulations
还没有普及到这些地区
have yet to reach these parts.
孩子们在新家危险的攀爬
Parents are surprisingly relaxed
竟没有引起家长们丝毫的担心
as their children explore their limits in the new home.
屋内火焰燃烧  屋外风景怡人...
住在这个美丽的森林里  我们十分满足
凭借知识  技艺和创新
Through knowledge, skill and ingenuity
雨林居民们已经适应了他们的生存环境
rainforest people have mastered their environment.
他们与环境和谐融洽
They live in tune with their surroundings
表现出对自然的尊重
and show it a respect
在许多其他地方已不复存在
that's being lost elsewhere.
他们不寻常的生活
Their remarkable lives
提醒着我们  没有自然就没有我们
remind us that we are nothing without nature.
人类星球
镜头背后的故事
记录巴布亚人建造树屋
Documenting the Papuan tree house build
是丛林拍摄组最富挑战的工作
was the most challenging shoot for the Jungles team.
为了在树顶拍摄  他们准备了两周
They came prepared for two weeks filming in the tree-tops,
但进展不顺时
but when things went wrong,
都是科罗威人挽救了大局
it was the Korowai who saved the day.
拉哈雨村庄  巴布亚岛
南纬05°30′51″  东经139°17′17″
为了拍摄这段影像  摄影师嘉文・瑟斯顿
This shoot took cameraman Gavin Thurston,
研究员瑞秋・金丽和制片人汤姆・修琼斯
researcher Rachael Kinley and producer Tom Hugh-Jones
深入到世界上几乎未被开发过的丛林
to some of the least explored jungles in the world.
路上大概需要五天
We're about five days into the trip,
我们刚刚顺利飞抵这里
we had a safe flight in,
嘉文・瑟斯顿
摄影师
我们受到了当地人热情的欢迎
we had a very good welcome committee,
我相信还要走上三天才能抵达目的地
and I believe it's about a three-day walk from here.
现在回不去了
No going back now.
尽管有当地挑夫帮我们减轻了负担
Though local porters help lighten the load,
可是在松软潮湿的丛林里徒步前进
trekking through the swampy jungle
远比我们想象的艰难
proves tougher than expected.
我刚才在想  如果他跳下水
I thought, if he's going in,
我们也得表示愿意跟着下水
we've got to show willing, haven't we?
我本来是打算帮忙的
I was going to come and help,
结果自己一脚陷了进去
but I've just fallen in.
但是为了为期仅仅两周的拍摄
But with only two weeks' filming,
他们必须日夜兼程
they have to push on.
终于  全体摄制组到达拉哈雨村庄
The crew eventually arrive at Lahayu's village
并受到科罗威人的热烈欢迎
to a warm welcome, Korowai style.
你们好  我亲爱的朋友们
这位是妮卡纳
This is Ninkana,
瑞秋・金丽
《人类星球》研究员
我们刚开始了长达五分钟的握手礼
we are beginning the five minutes of handshake
这似乎是你和某人见面时必不可少的
that seems to be necessary when you meet someone.
该谈谈正经事了
Then it's time to talk business.
阿罗姆・拉哈雨
村落首领
我会把建房的大树指给客人们看...
如果他们赞成这地点  我们就在那里建
嘉文之前去过一些偏远地带
Gavin's already spotted some local wildlife
拍摄野生动物
in unusual places.
这是纳塞  如果我发音正确的话
This is Nasai, if I've got his name right.
他戴着这个很神奇的
He's got these amazing, um,
从一只犀鸟身上摘来的毛冠
apart from an amazing hornbill
护着睾丸
penis sheath,
旁边有一些羽毛
he's got these feathers on the side here.
凤头鹦鹉
我想应该是只葵花凤头鹦鹉
I think that's the sulphur-crested cockatoo.
很吵的那种  对吗  还有什么
Noisy, yeah? What else?
凤冠鸽
鸽子
Pigeon?
那是犀鸟
And the hornbill?
差不多了  今天的自然课到此结束
There we are, so that's today's nature lesson!
摄制人员前去查看
The crew go to inspect the ironwood tree
铁木  坚硬的树木和乔木
科罗威人选定的铁木
the Korowai have chosen.
科罗威人找到了一棵很不错的树
Well, the Korowai have found a really good tree.
他们决定在离地面70英尺的树上
It's probably about 70 feet up to where they plan
建造一间树屋
to build the tree house.
看上去不错
It's looking good.
为了给摄像机架个位置
A line is fired into a nearby tree
我们从附近一棵大树拉起一根线
to rig a camera position
但绳索被缠住了
but the rope gets caught.
他们的一个人正往那里爬
One of these guys has just shinned right up there.
这种攀爬方式真令人难以置信
It's unbelievable climbing.
我只能说  如果是别人这样爬上去
All I can say is, if that was anybody else up there,
我的心一定都提到嗓子眼了
my heart would be in my throat,
但他看上去非常轻松自在
but he just looks so at ease.
多亏了科罗威人  问题解决了
Problem solved, thanks to the Korowai.
现在绳索问题解决了
Now the ropes are up,
嘉文成了另一个焦点
it's Gavin's turn to impress.
我想这些人一定很惊讶
I think these guys are fascinated
我们爬上一棵树竟需要这么多装备
by how much paraphernalia we need to get up a tree.
尤其是我还无法熟练使用它们
Especially when I can't do it properly.
科罗威人开始以惊人的速度建造房屋
The Korowai begin building at an astonishing rate,
使得嘉文不得不拼命追赶他们的进度
leaving Gavin struggling to keep up.
当他终于进入状态时
Just as he gets into the swing of things,
一场大雨不期而至
rain stops play.
真不敢相信雨已经整整下了17个小时
It's been raining for 17 hours solid, I can't believe it.
在雨天攀爬非常危险
When it's this wet it's not safe for them to climb,
木头都很滑
the logs are really slippery.
地下水位已经上升了不少
The water table has risen so much now
到处都是水  我们只能站在水里
we've got standing water everywhere,
还有一个更为不幸的消息就是
and the other detail you probably don't want to know
这雨不仅下了很久  而且雨势很大
is that the long drop too is completely full.
因为工作停滞不前
With work at a standstill,
摄制小组被邀请到家里做客
the crew are invited for a social visit.
"这就是儿时的梦想
'It's a childhood dream.
"在我最初的记忆里
'It's one of my first memories
"大概六七岁左右
"--when I was about six or seven,
"就想在花园里的苹果树上
"building a tree house about four foot off the ground
"建造一个离地四英尺的小树屋
"in an apple tree in the garden
"如今我要拍摄这些建造小树屋的能手了"
"and here I am coming to film the world experts."
所有的科罗威人的房屋都有男女分区
All Korowai houses are split into gender zones
而在女士这边
and, on the women's side,
瑞秋很受关注
Rachael's attracting a lot of attention.
她们似乎想把我打扮得更本土一点
They seem to be wanting to get me to dress a bit like them.
很快她看上去就有点当地味道了
Before long she's going native.
比预期的更像些
A little more than expected.
裙子系紧后
With the skirt safely fastened,
她就可以把裤子脱掉了
all that's left is for her to lose her trousers.
我们花了两个小时与他们亲密相处
We've had two hours of bonding with these people.
就这样坐下来  逐渐了解这座村落
It's just been really nice to sit down
汤姆・修琼斯
《人类星球》制片人
和他们分享一些笑话
and get to know the tribe
让他们嘲笑嘲笑我们
and to share some jokes with them,
了解他们的生活
let them laugh at us
这感觉真好
and see a bit of their life.
雨停了  科罗威人继续工作
When the rain stops, the Korowai get going
可是嘉文却被他的绳索齿轮耽误了
but Gavin's being encumbered by all his gear.
我真想知道以前有没有人拍到过
I wonder if anybody's ever filmed
挂在绳子上心脏病发作
a heart attack on a rope before.
一旦到达树顶
Once at the top of the tree,
嘉文的设备就很管用了
Gavin's kit comes into its own.
这个装置很不错  叫做树架
This is quite a clever device, called a tree pod.
上面有一些爪
It's got a couple of spikes
把它捆在树上
and when you strap it to the tree
就能形成一个很稳固的底座
you get a really good solid base.
再把摄像机架在上面
The camera goes on top of there.
他们选定的那棵建造小屋的大树
The tree they've chosen to put the tree house in,
是方圆百里最高的树
turns out it's the tallest tree for a good few hundred metres.
我们想要的效果
And one thing we wanted to do
就是可以拍到
is be able to see
树屋所处的大环境
the tree house in its environment,
拍到它直冲云霄
in the canopy,
拍出居高临下的感觉
and give a sense of height.
房屋至少有十层楼高
It must be getting on for ten storeys high
用的是枝条和藤蔓
and just made out of sticks and rattan.
真是一项不可思议的工程
It's quite an incredible bit of engineering.
在整个建造树上小屋的过程中
The whole time they've been building this tree house,
有一些非常惊险的瞬间
there have just been really scary moments.
那里有棵他们想推倒的大树
Right now there's quite a large tree they're trying to fell
但又担心它向小屋的方向倒下
but they're worried it might fall towards the tree house
从而带倒树梯
and take out the ladder.
所以不能全体出动
So instead of everybody getting out the tree house,
而是由三个人手执长杆
there's three guys with long poles
来推动大树
just pushing it out the way
下面还有两个人用藤条牵拉大树
and they've got two more down here with a bit of rattan
希望它可以往
pulling it, in the hope that
远离平台的一边倒下
it will go away from the platform,
一旦方向错误
but if it goes the wrong way,
这三个人必死无疑
those three guys are going to die!
有一棵树倒下了
Another tree falls.
这次位置有些太靠近了
This time it's a little too close for comfort.
幸运的是他们的判断准确无误
Luckily, they judged that one right
没有冲我们这面来
and it didn't come our way.
工程即将完工
The building's near completion,
嘉文还要拍一组小屋大全景
but Gavin still has to shoot the big reveal.
我们要从小屋所在的大树拉一根线出来
We've set up a line from the tree the tree house is in
穿越至我拍摄用的树架所在的地方
across to where I was filming from the tree pod.
把摄影移动车挂在线上
We're going to put the cable dolly on
拍出一组可以看到小屋
and get a really nice pull back
处在云端之下的后拉镜头
to reveal the tree house right up in the canopy.
求求你了  宝贝
Please, baby.
它不动了
It won't go anywhere.
发生什么了
What has happened?
它死机了
It's died!
这可是第一次
For the first time ever.
太糟了
Oh!
科罗威人又一次拯救了我们
Yet again, the Korowai come to the rescue.
这是科罗威的传统手工艺品
Traditional Korowai craftsmanship,
一根末端绑上枯枝的长棍
a stick with another little bit of stick tied on the end.
过来宝贝
Come on, baby!
嘉文及时在晚饭前收回了摄影移动车
Gavin retrieves the camera dolly in time for supper.
食物都快吃完了
Food supplies are running low
所以科罗威人奉上了一道当地美食
so the Korowai serve up a local delicacy.
西米蛴螬
Sago grubs.
是生活在西谷米里的
They're basically giant
一种甲虫的幼虫
beetle grubs that live inside the sago palms.
而且很美味
And they are a delicacy.
最后喀吱嚼到它们的牙齿时
The crunch at the end when you chew their teeth
可能感觉不太好
perhaps isn't the best.
不过除此之外  还算不错
But other than that they are all right.
你一直说你需要吃蛋白质
You kept saying you wanted protein.
他要吐了
He's gagging!
我觉得吃上去有点像鱼子酱
I think they taste like caviar.
嘴里有那种清脆的爆裂声
It's got that pop in your mouth.
-你喜欢吃吗  -嗯
- Do you like them? - Mmmm.
-你可以吃我的  -谢谢  多来点
- You can have the rest, then. - Ah! Thanks. Some more!
对于西米蛴螬的最终体会是
The verdict on the sago grubs is,
它们是可食用的
they are edible
但也实在是太令人作呕了
but they are actually pretty disgusting!
我还在嚼着呢
I'm still chewing!
今天是最后一天
It's the final day and
也是嘉文拍摄大全景的最后一次机会
Gavin's last chance to shoot the grand finale.
今天可是天时地利  阳光耀眼
Today, it's all come together. The sun's shining,
大家都在帮忙
the guys are being helpful
摄像移动车也工作正常
and the cable dolly is behaving itself
希望这将是这个节目
and hopefully, this is the
和这组镜头的最后一次拍摄
end shot for the sequence and the programme.
亲眼目睹了在如此高处建造房屋的全过程
It's just been incredible seeing the whole process
令人感觉不可思议
of how they build the house this high up in the canopy.
他们似乎非常适应新环境
They seem to have settled in very well.
大多数人都已经睡着了
Most of them are asleep now.
事实上我也精疲力尽
I'm knackered as well, actually.
和科罗威人一起度过的这段时间
Spending time with the Korowai
使得嘉文对生命又有了新的思考
has given Gavin a different perspective on life.
相较于他们的技能与知识
I judge my own inadequacies
我重新审视了自己的不足
against their expertise and knowledge.
来到这里
You come here
你穿着靴子以防蛇咬
and you've got boots on in case of snake bites,
你涂着防晒霜以防烈日
you've got sun cream on because of the sun,
你有两根保险绳  这样一根断了
you've got twin safety ropes to make sure, if one fails,
你还能抓住另一根
you are caught on the other one.
而这些人
And these guys, OK,
也许死亡率很高
maybe they have a higher mortality rate,
但他们的生活方式却更自由
but they're much freer in their lifestyle.
他们在树林间上上下下
You know, they're shinning up and down these trees.
我更愿意像他们一样
I'd much rather live a shorter,
活得虽然不长  却更为充实
fuller life, like they do out here.